um
there's nothing else I had thought about
something that I thought might be useful and
and
so you often talk about enduring things
on the right level hmm
so
well first what exactly needs to be
endured and then what's the right level
and then what's the right level
exactly and
and then well I suppose yeah why is it
important what does it result in
yeah so uh
what needs to be endured is basically
the any type of
any type of
pressure there's always a degree of
pressure so you're not enduring some random
so you're not enduring some random
abstract ideas for things that are not
uh whose emotional weight is not felt
so it's always that's why it's like the
importance like
um all things Converge on feelings
that's basically where you find what you
need to endure uh
what you need to not act out of
um
and uh
so yeah so the the types of pressure
you know you can
you can describe him in your own way in
a way like whatever pressures you but
fundamentally they're gonna fall into
five categories
the categories of the five hindrances
but I don't want to say are you into
five hindrances because people
have read extensive about five entrances
and then they'll just
slot what I said into that idea of aha
if I had just right this is how you deal
with it no it's like you find
you find your existence always Within
one of those
it always has to be pressured by
something unless you've like completely
in first genre basically there always
has to be a degree of pressure
so you see whether it's the pressure in
regard to sensuality
whether you are removable in regard to
that pressure whether it's the pressure
regard to your will irritation
sloth laziness indolence
whether it's in regard to doubt there is
always something where your feelings are
converging on
either craving for more pleasure craving
for less pain going for Less doubt and
so on
so that needs to be recognized as a
thing as a state of mind as a
fundamental Direction
Direction
that you are in yeah
what does it mean to endure it on the
right level well means basically to see
it to its extent as phenomenon
to see it as a thing there
as we spoke before independent of space
or time all your actions that come out
of it it's just there on its own
and to that extent it has arisen and to
that extent it's manifested and you need
to kind of see like people might
recognize Central desire in their mind
or real will but they recognize it with
all the like with a whole set of
assumptions oh they still will it's in
my brain it's in my mind it's the
hormones it's the electrons it's the
body it's this it's that it's not it's
your mode of existence at the time fully
completely as the entire picture that is
your basis the mind of your will
the mind of lust the mind of doubt
so you need to see it
um
on the level of the Mind
in other words not as a thought in your
head like inside of this head that's part of
like inside of this head that's part of
this body but pretty much recognize it
whether it's the body head inside out
all the Notions of space are secondary
to the enduring level of the pressure of
certain feeling that you have at a time
so it needs to be seen as a phenomenon
independent of space and time needs to
be recognized in its own presence so to
speak and then obviously the only way you can
and then obviously the only way you can
recognize that is if you have not been
acting out of it habitually which is
already creating furthering that
division inside outside sense organ
sense objects from here to there in
between the two left and right
but all of that is within the enduring
capsule of a certain hindrance
so you can't put a hindrance in front of
you as an object of your experience and
you certainly can't measure it in space
and time
but you can certainly you can you can
feel its pressure you can feel its
weight and that abstract kind of recognition
and that abstract kind of recognition
seemingly abstract recognition it's
abstract because the mind is not
training regard to it but
if you were to stop and ask yourself oh
is there a like are there even traces of
centrality or is there a possibility of
a non-orician central desire to arise in
me do I see that like oh if I if I were
to do this this and this would
sensuality arise recognizing that that's
a phenomenon really such that
possibility that reality that that
liability and you need to see it
enduring there regardless of what you do
where you look where you sit how you go
you need to see it independent of your
movement of your body of your division
in out mind yours World science
everything else that's what means you
need to see this phenomenal you need to
recognize that it's really such in its
own extent
wherever it has a reason whichever way
it has arisen so you don't need to
perceive it directly with your eyes in
order for it to be real you just need to
be aware of it and you are aware of it
so when you reckon there's also anything
I can be aware of means it's real as
such within that level within that
domain sure it's not real in the domain
of sites because I can't see it there it
doesn't exist there but it's certainly
really in the domain of thoughts in the
domain of images
in the domain of feeling and so on
and that's as we spoke before that's
what the honest one is yeah so that
would be the right level
so you start seeing the hindrances first
as the cornerstones that are kind of
converging Point kind of the the what
we're trying to make you act or you're
trying to
um
prolonged Pleasures avoid pains so even
if there is not an acute sensual desire
present as I said before
if you're still valuing sensuality
hoping it will come hoping you'll get
some more later on and so on that is
still uh operational within the
hindrance of central desire
within that direction we did that
pressure why because the notion of pleasure in
why because the notion of pleasure in
that most kind of remote mental sense of
an image of agreeability is not seen
real as such it's not seen real as an
image that directs your experience and
then makes you crave for more
it's seen as a fleeting thought in
regard to the more kind of real senses
and even realer gratification that I get
to an account of sense objects but all
of that is known only because you have
their thoughts there throughout that
whole project of Json centrality like
how would you know that touching
something is Pleasant before you touch
it
how would you crave for it how would you
crave for its pleasure before you
actually made the physical contact with
seemingly where the pleasure comes from
which is the sense object that would be
in conceivable
yet here you are acting protecting
fighting together to get that sense of
touch side sounds melted touch whatever
it is before you actually touch it
contact it
because pleasure is already rooted in
your mind that's already that image that
exists it defines everything else yet
you think it's just an abstract fleeting
thought you don't you don't recognize the the
you don't you don't recognize the the
weight of it
and person wouldn't recognize it because
they would just be habitual acting out
of it and as I said directing out of it
you are perpetuating that
um gratuitous completely false division
of oh this is inside this is outside
that's real this is not not as real and
so on
um but if you start recognizing the
noise hold on it's really such like how
do I know that this is Pleasant before I
even look at it
I don't know where to look for pleasure
pleasure comes from the contact of the
sense objects onto my sense organs
only time I can know it is while I'm
being contacted yet here I am planning
devising how to get it in the future
and you're equally gripped by that fever
of sensual desire
in your thoughts even before you
actually touch the objects that you
crave for
quite often after touching the object so
tasting the object you pay for it's like
it's a letdown it wasn't as good as your
thoughts were presenting the pleasure
there so it needs to be seen really such on
so it needs to be seen really such on
that level
and that's how you stop gratuitously
emphasizing the the scent objects But
first you need to be withdrawn from them
same with your will again like you know
you might you might have a hateful
attitude towards side sounds smell takes
to touch but fundamentally that attitude
precedes the actual contact with those hateful
the actual contact with those hateful
objects it's already in your mental
framework the disagreeability of it the
annoyance the irritation and you don't
see that phenomenon really such enduring
there and by overlooking it that's it you are
and by overlooking it that's it you are
under its pressure that's all it takes
look past the hindrance
don't recognize it where it is to the
extent that it is really such
independent of space and time
uh that's all it takes for it to to to
hinder you
just do not see it
you're already under its influence
and then the goal of that would be
exactly exactly that
um
freedom for pressure
freedom from five modes of pressure can
assume
so like as you said
all of what you just said would be
completely invisible
if you're acting out with these things
yeah it does not exist so then
it might be useful to
clarify what constitutes acting out
because it might be easy to
assume that it's only kind of relatively
coarse as in if I go and get the thing I
want and eat this work or you know see
it or whatever
but
suppose I want I don't know to give an
example like you could even
somebody could listen to this listen to
what you're saying and
even just I suppose you know a
pressuring kind of thought comes up and
now you start trying to remember what
did he say and how do I know how to do
it and that's already acting out yeah so
see first the course the course acting out
first the course the course acting out
has to stop so preset sends restraint
it's just not negotiable like gamma does
not exist
there is nowhere for dhamma to apply
unless that basis is developed
beforehand so it's just it's not up for
debate now acting out exactly so there
will already be a hindrance of doubt oh
we're doing Luca how do I see you're not
alive how do you do that and the skill
there inevitably you're going to be
you're trying to deal with what
hindrance you're going to get caught
into another one and so on then you're
gonna get angry then you're gonna try to
overcome that Pain by craving for
centrality because that's your only
means of Escape you know then you're
gonna go sleepy because it's just too
much and so on but the point is that not
to deal with an individual hindrance in
that course manner but to recognize I
mean you can initially sure like if if
there is a hindrance of sensuality well
don't go in the objects that will be
making it worse
if you are completely just just sleepy
and lazy well get off the comfortable
couch don't lay on it because obviously
it's gonna it's just common sense but
that that's that's nothing it's not
gonna put any hindrance what would
approve them eventually is to recognize
that whichever it is present it's
present through the pressure
so like you might start by being gripped
by the hindrance of Doubt oh he said I'm
a series
hold on
my whole desire to see this on the right
level it's already coming out of a
pressure oh that's what I need to do not act out
oh that's what I need to do not act out
of the pressure so by recognizing the
pressure you won't act out of it why not
act out of it not acting out of it you
get to recognize it and then if your
mind moves into like craving for Central
pleasure again oh again that's a
pressure I don't care what
what wants as its object all I care is
it I'm pressured I'm under its kind of
weight push in a certain direction
that's what I need to see I need to see
that pressure real as such there is
pressure present
so like and then endure the pressure in
that sense because see once you see
through the hindrance the pressure it's
Force basically where we're kind of
where it has influence over you the
actual object and the content of the
hindrance you already surmounted
by recognizing the pressure of it you're
already not that much directed on
Central objects as you were before same
with the doubt sure if you kind of
Overlook the pressure again forget try
to get rid of it you're going to fall
into the objects presented ah doubt and
figure out your sense of the turanga but
if you actually recognize the pressure
as as a necessary basis for any content
of the hindrance you are already
uninvolved with the content you're
already closer to recruiting it yes
yes like if you recognize
pressure in any
in any way for anything you don't
necessarily even need to kind of I don't
know classify it until exactly that's
what you can describe it in the wrong
way I mean the suit is described five
hindrances because that's about I'm sure
not all the monks who necessarily see
them back in the day they had probably
their own ways but what they all had in
common was the the pressure so where
would where would you find that pressure
so where would you find if there is a
presence of pressure or possibility of
the pressure increasing and so on where
do you look for it what is the level for
that feeling feeling exactly so you would
feeling feeling exactly so you would
know that if there is a feeling to the
degree that there is a feeling to that
degree there is a pressure
any feeling any feeling yeah any feeling
yeah so pleasant feeling that's a pressure
so pleasant feeling that's a pressure
unpleasant feeling that's a pressure
neutral feeling that's pressure yeah
pressure then we're known it's not
unpleasant when not known it's unpleasant
when not known it's unpleasant
but fundamentally there is always a
pressure for as long well for as long as
you're not another hand obviously it's
not always the same degree or pressure
for somebody whose mind is free
partially free and so on he's obviously
going to have less things pressuring him
because they're less fetish there but
the point is uh you need to recognize
that oh it's not like oh I'm free from
pressure now and I'm not in other that's
impossible so there's always going to be a degree
so there's always going to be a degree
of feeling to that extent there is a
degree of pressure to that extent there
is a potential for hindrance if you if
you if you don't see that pressure on
the level
that it exists
as a phenomenon neither inside nor
outside neither in my head nor in the
world but here really such I mean the
most real thing directs your whole
existence shapes your whole life
decisions and everything else
emotional needs and so on Impressions if
you don't see it on that level that's
what it starts to hinder you that's
where its counterpart starts to hinder
you but if you see it as a pressure
but if you see it as a pressure
it cannot
it's it's held it's basically put in
place it's recognized for what it is
the Beautiful the ugly the lack of
energy restlessness again like natural
restlessness again like natural
phenomenon in a way but they don't need
to they hinder you when you are not
developed in regard to their pressure If
you developed in regards to the pressure
they cease to be hindrances but those
things that were hindering you
those those contents those those objects
they do remain
yeah there's the suit I don't remember
the reference now maybe I can
it describes exactly that when rightly
attended they cease to be the hindrance
but they remain that which they were
before they hindered you
but obviously you don't start unhindered
you don't start by having a pure sign of
beauty that then develops into
sensuality no no no no my not flee from
hindrances starts with sensuality so you
can only undo the degree of that
sensuality and then discover that there
is a pure sign of beauty a pure sign of
agreeable but attended rightly cannot bring lust
but attended rightly cannot bring lust
to increase in you impossible
attended rightly to what well to that
sign to that pressure to to its
characteristics and its core
well I think yeah it's
it's kind of about seeing what genuinely
helps you in that sense as a not just
kind of doing what you
have thought you are supposed to do
there can be a difference
well it's again
if you think you should do what you're
supposed to do you're not looking for
the pressure you're just acting out to
get rid of the discomfort which is
exactly what hindrance wants you to do
that's the whole point
hinges doesn't care if you follow
through and how far you go as long as
you act out of the pressure that's all
it matters you are already caught you're
already hindered
how far you go and whether you get your
gratification or that's really relevant
that's only important to you because
you're already caught
if you were to see that pressure
as a phenomenon like you were describing
just now
correctly that it would not be that
pressure will not be felt hmm
and if you think you see it rightly as a
phenomenon but there is still that pressure you are
but there is still that pressure you are
overlooking something yeah and that's
the practice there because initially
naturally you emphasize your view that's
where the views are kind of the most
plain worthy thing or the best thing
that can feel
see like
you have a criteria whereby
when the pressure is seen rightly it's
easy to pressure you
but it might not feel right to you
so if you still emphasize that oh it
doesn't feel right I need to see it
again until it feels right
that's already your view being put first
yeah that's already under the pressure
so that's where that kind of
intelligence and understanding and
discernment starts to sort of um play Play the part
starts to sort of um play Play the part
where you reckon is okay
I know what's right though I understood
that rightly seeing pressure means not
being pressured there and then while the
pressure remains that which pressures
you remain let's say that way so I just
need to abstain
and refrain from overly
defining it so to slot and fit what I
expected fitting to be
and just pretty much out of Faith stick
to the right level because you reckon as
well but hold on my goal is not to
satisfy my my my my
intellectual need for clarity and fit
but my goal is to be free from suffering
so I've come halfway up and there is
freedom from suffering to that to death
at that degree at that extent
but now I kind of carry on more to fit
it even better in a satisfactory manner
so it's like but if I don't do that I
still have nothing to lose
if I don't give in to that pressure to
overly clarify uh freedom from doubt and
this hindrance and that hindrance but
actually just stay with where the
pressure is
recognize it to the extent that I'm not
pressured towards things that that he
wants me to go it's like yeah I have
nothing to lose there like it's
uncomfortable only because of your need
to kind of overly do it overshoot the
mark so that's that's something like I was
so that's that's something like I was
going to ask you like
um
what body posture are you now
sitting like did you have to stop and
think about it did you have to get up
you know you already know that
so it's like sometimes when there is too
much of a desire to like figure it out
and understand you stop seeing the
obvious that is still there such as body
is still there even if you don't
explicitly think about it
so it's to learn how to keep seeing it
without explicitly thinking about it
that's the point
and that's the the body postures
um that you can contemplate or the
nature of the body the universal nature
of the organs regardless of the
situation regardless of the emotional
it's on because those things would set
in
so then they become that with your body
is that's how you see it correctly
but the body is already there the whole
the way of attending to this here and
now it's already on the basis of body
being in a certain position Here and Now
it's like it cannot be elsewhere
so it's more like
you undoing that expectation to find the
body only after you think about it on
your own terms
because it's already there so it's like
I can think about it to find it or I can
refrain from thinking and look it's
already there
and then that's the direction that
everything else goes first yeah you need
to pick it up with your craving
to know what to look for but then if
you're doing it rightly time raccoon is
how I'll find it by not actually
actively engaging with this craving in
that direction but yeah pick it up so I
know what to recognize but recognition
is over there
you know what I found
all kind of a good way of putting it is
but that's a
that's a
foreign is that even the recognition of
the body already there is because the
body is already there yeah
so
like if you understand that then
basically well it's it's the question of
the music of understanding it once the
question of training yourself to keep
seeing it that way say you do
you do
you are able to
endure things on the right level to the
extent that the pressure is not felt
then is there something else you need to
do
um
well
you just need to make sure that you
always stay above those pressures then
more you need to kind of do on top of
that well there is but that can become
only apparent once you're thoroughly
above the pressures
but yeah the suitors do say what you
need to do when you get established in
not being moved by any pressure when
it's completely economous
peaceful immovable quite delightful now
you regard that the same way as you did
the pressures
oh this is also a debt a boil a dart
Affliction I'm better off even not
having this
so then your mind turns away even from
that first genre
and that's where the whole all of the
Usos will have to be uprooted yeah
nothing can remain lingering
in order to do that yeah first establish
yourself in the entire piece that no
hindrance can move you and then this
will kind of
I mean they always say it would come
naturally but with all the suitors that
we already know there is no way that
then you would not oh hold on well this
too actually it would be better if
well it would be better if it's if it
were not there to begin with certainly
because any experience that arises is
not worth playing it it's not worth
having it's not worth the lighting or
finding safety and even this pure
purified freed experience from all the
pressures all the compulsions all the
hindrances all the doubts and everything
else not mine not for me not I am
because that experience of being free
from pressures and hindrances Israel as
such it's a phenomenon enduring there
phenomenon where the directionality of
affirming or denying is completely
evened out so it's completely
even there is no more leaning forward nor
there is no more leaning forward nor
against
but it's still real as such
that middle ground is really such
and if you see it means oh you will know
it as impermanent unownable
rightly developed but equally not worth
owning either